Here is a really cool way of encoding numbers using dots and parentheses that you might not have seen before.
Pause here and see if you can figure it out.
First off, the primes follow a pattern,
so it’s a good idea to look at the factorizations.
If we look at numbers
with no repeating factors,
they only have single nested parentheses or dots,
which is just zeros and ones.
Furthermore, numbers with repeating factors are nested more heavily,
so the encoding likely involves their powers.
If we look at the full factorization, the encoding becomes quite clear –
the powers of the primes correspond
to the inner sequence of dots and brackets.
For example, 5 is 2^0 times 3^0 times 5^1
and 9 is 2^0 times 3^2 .
Thanks for watching!