Perfect graphs are a family of graphs with various interesting properties, notably that many problems that are NP complete on general graphs can be solved efficiently on perfect graphs.
There exist various characterizations of perfect graphs.
The one that we’ll be focusing on in this video is the Weak perfect graph theorem, proved in 1972 by László Lovász.
Before proceeding to the proof, there are quite a few definitions that we have to know in order to understand it.
You might already know some of them, so feel free to skip forward in the video accordingly.
A complement of a graph G is a graph Ḡ, such that each two vertices are adjacent in Ḡ, if and only if they are not adjacent in G.
A clique is a subgraph of a graph, such that each two vertices are adjacent.
Analogically, an independent set in a graph is a set of vertices such that no two are adjacent.
We’ll also denote ω(G) to be the size of the largest clique in G (also called the clique number),
and α(G) to be the size of the largest independent set in G (also called the independence number).
These two concepts are closely tied together.
Considering a complement of a graph, we see that each independent set becomes a clique, and vice versa.
A graph H is an induced subgraph of the graph G, if and only if we can get H by removing zero or more vertices (along with their edges) from G.
Additionally, it is a proper induced subgraph, if we remove one or more vertices.
The chromatic number χ(G) of a graph G is the minimum number of colors we need to color the graph’s vertices, such that no two adjacent vertices have the same color.
Finally, a graph G is perfect (informally denoted G⋆), if and only if ∀H ≤ G : χ(H) = ω(H).
With the definitions out of the way, let’s make a few observations about how perfect graphs behave, that will help us understand the proof better.
Firstly, ∀H ≤ G : ω(H) ≤ χ(H), because each maximum clique has to contain as many colors as its vertices.
For perfect graphs, this becomes an equality from definition.
Secondly, if a graph is perfect, then each of its induced subgraphs is perfect too.
This again follows immediately from the definition of a perfect graph, since something is true for each of its induced subgraphs.
As for examples, some common families of graphs that are perfect include complete graphs (where χ and ω is the number of vertices)
and bipartite graphs (where χ is either 1 when it has no edges, or 2 if it does, either of which works).
Some families that are not perfect include cycles of odd length ≥ 5 (because ω = 2 and χ = 3) and even wheel graphs of length ≥ 6 (because ω = 3 and χ = 4).
Our first lemma is actually a characterization of a perfect graph.
It states that the graph G is perfect, if and only if ∀H ≤ G contains an independent set, such that each maximum clique in H contains a vertex from this set (called a vast independent set).
The left-to-right implication is pretty straight-forward.
Since χ(G) = ω(G), each largest clique contains all possible colors.
That means we can choose any color and let the independent set be all vertices of that color.
By definition, such independent set is vast.
The right-to-left implication can be proven using induction on the number of vertices.
The base case is trivially true.
For the induction step, assume that we’ve proven the statement for all smaller graphs.
Let G be a graph such that each induced subgraph of G contains a vast independent set.
Let I be a vast independent set in G, and H be the induced subgraph obtained from G by removing I.
Observe that ω(H) = ω(G) − 1, since all maximum cliques in G contain one vertex from I.
By induction, H is perfect, so there exists a vertex coloring of H using ω(G) − 1 colors.
Adding the vertices of I back, we can color all of them using one extra color and obtain a coloring of G using ω(G) colors.
Our second lemma states that if G is perfect, then any graph constructed from G by expanding a vertex is also perfect.
By expanding, we mean that we replace the vertex with a complete graph of any size (denoted Kp) and connect it to all of its neighbours accordingly.
For proof, observe that expanding a vertex to Kp is equivalent to repeatedly expanding it to K2,
so it’s enough to prove that expanding a vertex to K2 preserves perfectness.
Let’s again use induction on the number of vertices in G.
The base case is expanding a single vertex to K2, which is perfect.
Now we have some graph G and a vertex v that we expand to v, v′, forming G′. We’ll examine two cases.
Case one is that expanding increases ω (obviously only by one).
This is fine, since we can now use an additional color on v′, so G′ is still perfect.
Case two is that expanding doesn’t increase ω.
In this case, let’s take a χ coloring of G.
Looking at the set of vertices with the same color as v, we know that this must be a vast independent set (since each clique contains all of the colors).
However, v is not a part of a maximum clique, because otherwise ω would have increased.
Removing all vertices of this color besides v will decrease ω by one and, by induction, give a χ − 1 coloring of the smaller graph.
Adding the vertices back using the removed color, including the not-yet-added v′ proves the second case.
Now we’ll finally prove the main theorem. It states that a graph G is perfect, if and only if Ḡ is perfect.
First, notice that although this is an equivalence, we only need to prove one implication, since the statement is symmetrical.
We’ll prove the implication by contradiction. Let’s take the smallest graph G⋆ that is perfect but Ḡ isn’t.
Because Ḡ isn’t perfect, it follows from lemma 1 that it has an induced subgraph H without a vast independent set.
Furthermore, it must be that H = Ḡ, because if H⋆ < Ḡ, then H̄ would be perfect (since H̄ < G⋆ and G⋆ is perfect).
This would, however, be a contradiction with the minimality of (G⋆,Ḡ).
We now know that Ḡ doesn’t have a vast independent set, meaning that each independent set misses at least one maximum clique.
Translated into the language of the graph G, each clique misses at least one maximum independent set.
Let’s list all of the cliques in G⋆, calling them Q1 to Qt.
From the previous observation, for each clique Ql, we have a maximum independent set Il, such that they are disjoint.
We’ll now do something that seems very strange, but is actually the core idea behind the proof.
For each vertex v in G⋆, let f(v) denote the number of the maximum independent sets that it’s in.
By expanding each vertex v to size f(v), we create a new graph G′⋆.
Now we know that G′⋆ is perfect, because G⋆ is perfect and any graph expanded from G⋆ is, using lemma 2, also perfect.
The rest of the proof is basically rearranging inequalities in order to show that χ(G′⋆) ≠ ω(G′⋆),
which would make G′⋆ not perfect, leading to a contradiction.
Let’s count the number of vertices of G′⋆.
Since the maximum independent sets from G⋆ don’t overlap in G′⋆ (from the way we expanded each vertex), it’s equal to t ⋅ α(G⋆).
Using this, we’ll calculate the lower bound for χ(G′⋆).
It must be greater than |V(G′⋆)|/α(G′⋆), because that is the most efficient use of the colors
(each color is not only an independent set, but also the largest one).
α(G′⋆) is, however, just α(G⋆), because expanding a vertex can’t increase the size of the maximum independent set.
Plugging the value for vertices and simplifying gives us t.
We’ll now calculate the upper bound for ω(G′⋆).
Let Q′ be the largest clique in G′⋆.
This clique must have been created from inflating some clique Q in G⋆.
Recall that each clique in G misses at least one maximum independent set.
This means, that ω(G′⋆) ≤ t − 1, because there can be at most one vertex for each independent set, except the one that we know it misses.
Combining those two inequalities, we get that ω(G′⋆) < χ(G′⋆),
meaning that G′⋆ is not perfect, reaching a contradiction and proving the theorem.
A stronger version of the theorem that we just proved is the Strong perfect graph theorem.
It states that a graph is perfect, if and only if it doesn’t contain an odd hole or an odd antihole greater than 3.
By hole, we mean an induced cycle and by antihole, we mean a complement to an induced cycle.
These two examples are, using this theorem, not perfect, since they each contain either a hole or an antihole of size 5.
We won’t be proving this theorem, since it took a 150-page paper released in 2002 to do so,
but we’ll observe that it immediately proves the Weak perfect graph theorem (from definition of a complement – holes become antiholes and vice versa).