Imagine you’re given n colors and a graph.
Your task is to find the number of colorings of vertices
such that adjacent vertices have different colors –
what would you do?
You could try to bruteforce the solution,
but that would only work for smaller ns.
Instead, we can calculate what is called a chromatic polynomial for this graph.
If we plug in n for any x,
we get the exact number of colorings.
Cool, right?
This, however, is just a special case of the much more interesting Tutte polynomial.
This two-variate polynomial is fascinating because besides colorings,
(x = 1, y = 1) counts the number of spanning trees,
(x = 2, y = 0) counts the number of acyclic orientations
and much more –
it is used for measuring network reliability,
for calculating linear codes
and even has ties to quantum field theory.
If you found this interesting and want to know more
(like how to actually calculate it),
I’d recommend you check out this neat handbook,
written by many experts in the field,
which contains a great overview of this polynomial’s many fascinating uses.
In any case, thanks for watching!